For more than 100 years,
لأكثر من 100 سنة،
the telephone companies have provided wiretapping assistance to governments.
وفرت شركات الهاتف المساعدة للحكومات للتنصت على مكالماتها .
For much of this time, this assistance was manual.
ولوقت كبير ،كانت هذه المساعدات يدوية .
Surveillance took place manually and wires were connected by hand.
وكانت المراقبات يدوياً وكانت الأسلاك موصولة باليد.
Calls were recorded to tape.
وكانت المكالمات تسجل على شريط .
But as in so many other industries,
ولكن كما هو الحال في العديد من الصناعات الأخرى،
computing has changed everything.
فإن الحوسبة قد غيرت كل شيء.
The telephone companies built surveillance features
بنت شركات الهاتف ميزات للمراقبة .
into the very core of their networks.
في صميم شبكاتها.
I want that to sink in for a second:
أريد منك أن تركز معي لثوان:
Our telephones and the networks that carry our calls
هواتفنا وشبكاتنا التي نتصل من خلالها
were wired for surveillance first.
تخضع للمراقبة أولاً .
First and foremost.
أولاً وقبل كل شيء .
So what that means is that when you're talking to your spouse,
مما يعني أنك عندما تتكلم مع زوجتك ،
your children, a colleague or your doctor on the telephone,
أطفالك، زميلك أو طبيبك على الهاتف،
someone could be listening.
قد يكون هناك شخص يسمعك .
Now, that someone might be your own government;
وهذا الشخص قد يكون حكومتك ;
it could also be another government, a foreign intelligence service,
أو حكومة أخرى ،أو دائرة الاستخبارات الخارجية،
or a hacker, or a criminal, or a stalker
أو القراصنة، أو مجرم، أو مطارد
or any other party that breaks into the surveillance system,
أو أي طرف آخر يخترق نظام المراقبة ،
that hacks into the surveillance system of the telephone companies.
لشركات الهاتف .
But while the telephone companies have built surveillance as a priority,
ولكن في حين أن شركات الهاتف بنت المراقبة كأولوية،
Silicon Valley companies have not.
فإن شركات وادي السيليكون لم تبنها.
And increasingly, over the last couple years,
وعلى نحو متزايد، على مدى السنوات القليلة الماضية،
Silicon Valley companies have built strong encryption technology
بنت شركات وادي السيليكون تقنية التشفير القوية
into their communications products
لمنتجات اتصالاتهم
that makes surveillance extremely difficult.
مما جعل المراقبة صعبة للغاية .
For example, many of you might have an iPhone,
على سبيل المثال، الكثير منكم قد يكون لديه آي فون،
and if you use an iPhone to send a text message
وإذا كنت تستخدم آي فون لإرسال رسالة نصية
to other people who have an iPhone,
للناس الآخرين الذين لديهم آي فون،
those text messages cannot easily be wiretapped.
فإن تلك الرسائل النصية لا يمكن بسهولة التنصت عليها.
And in fact, according to Apple,
وفي الواقع، وفقا لشركة آبل،
they're not able to even see the text messages themselves.
ليسوا قادرين حتى على رؤية الرسائل بأنفسهم .
Likewise, if you use FaceTime to make an audio call
وكذلك ، إذا كنت تستخدم فيس تايم لإجراء مكالمة صوتية
or a video call with one of your friends or loved ones,
أو مكالمة فيديو مع واحد من الأصدقاء أو الأحباء،
that, too, cannot be easily wiretapped.
ذلك، أيضا، لا يمكن التنصت عليها بسهولة.
And it's not just Apple.
ليست مجرد شركة أبل.
WhatsApp, which is now owned by Facebook
الواتس اب ، وهي مملوكة الآن من قبل الفيسبوك
and used by hundreds of millions of people around the world,
ويستخدمه مئات الملايين من الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم،
also has built strong encryption technology into its product,
كما قامت ببناء تكنولوجيا تشفيرقوية في منتجاتها،
which means that people in the Global South can easily communicate
وهو ما يعني أن الناس في جنوب الكرة الأرضية يمكنهم الاتصال بسهولة
without their governments, often authoritarian,
من دون أن تقوم حكوماتهم الاستبدادية عادةً،
wiretapping their text messages.
من التنصت على رسائلهم .
So, after 100 years of being able to listen to any telephone call --
وهكذا، بعد 100 سنة من التنصت على المكالمات الهاتفية -
anytime, anywhere --
في أي وقت وفي أي مكان --
you might imagine that government officials are not very happy.
وقد تتصور أن المسؤولون الحكوميين غير سعداء بذلك .
And in fact, that's what's happening.
وفي واقع الأمر، هذا ما يحدث.
Government officials are extremely mad.
المسؤولون الحكوميون منزعجون للغاية ،
And they're not mad because these encryption tools are now available.
وهم ليسوا منزعجين لأن أدوات التشفير هذه أصبحت متوفرة .
What upsets them the most
ما يزعجهم حقاً
is that the tech companies have built encryption features into their products
هو أن شركات التكنولوجيا بنت ميزات التشفير في منجاتها
and turned them on by default.
وشغلتها بشكل تلقائي.
It's the default piece that matters.
جزئية التلقائية هي الأهم هنا.
In short, the tech companies have democratized encryption.
وباختصار، فإن شركات التكنولوجيا لديها تشفير ديمقراطي .
And so, government officials like British Prime Minister David Cameron,
وهكذا، فإن مسؤولين حكوميين مثل رئيس الوزراء البريطاني ديفيد كاميرون،
they believe that all communications -- emails, texts, voice calls --
يعتقدون أن كل الاتصالات - البريد الإلكتروني، الرسائل، والمكالمات -
all of these should be available to governments,
كل هذه يجب أن تكون متاحة للحكومات،
and encryption is making that difficult.
والتشفير يجعل من ذلك شيئاً صعباً.
Now, look -- I'm extremely sympathetic to their point of view.
الآن، اسمعوا - أنا متعاطف جدًا مع وجهة نظرهم.
We live in a dangerous time in a dangerous world,
نحن نعيش في زمن خطير في عالم خطر،
and there really are bad people out there.
وهناك ناس سيئة فعلاً .
There are terrorists and other serious national security threats
فهناك إرهابيون وهناك تهديدات أمنية قومية خطيرة
that I suspect we all want the FBI and the NSA to monitor.
أتوقع أننا جميعا نريد أن يقوم مكتب التحقيقات الفدرالي ووكالة الأمن القومي بمراقبتها .
But those surveillance features come at a cost.
ولكن هذه المراقبة لها ضريبة.
The reason for that is
السبب في ذلك هو
that there is no such thing as a terrorist laptop,
أنه لا يوجد حاسوب إرهابي مثلاً
or a drug dealer's cell phone.
أو هاتف خلوي يتاجر بالمخدرات .
We all use the same communications devices.
كلنا يستخدم نفس وسائل الإتصال .
What that means is that if the drug dealers' telephone calls
مما يعني أنه إذا كان هناك تاجر المخدرات
or the terrorists' telephone calls can be intercepted,
أو إرهابي يستخدم هذه الوسائل فيجب أن يراقب ،
then so can the rest of ours, too.
وبالتالي يجب أن يراقب الكل أيضاً ،
And I think we really need to ask:
وأعتقد أننا نحتاج حقا أن نسأل:
Should a billion people around the world be using devices
هل يجب على مليار شخص حول العالم أن يستخدموا هذه الوسائل
that are wiretap friendly?
التي يتم التنصت عليها بشكل ودي ؟
So the scenario of hacking of surveillance systems that I've described --
وبالتالي فإن السيناريوعن قرصنة مراقبة الأنظمة التي تحدثت عنها -
this is not imaginary.
ليس وهميا.
In 2009,
في عام 2009،
the surveillance systems that Google and Microsoft built into their networks --
أنظمة المراقبة التي بنتها جوجل ومايكروسوفت في شبكاتها -
the systems that they use to respond to lawful surveillance requests
والتي تستخدمها للرد على طلبات المراقبة القانونية
from the police --
من الشرطة --
those systems were compromised by the Chinese government,
انكشفت من قبل الحكومة الصينية،
because the Chinese government wanted to figure out
لأن الحكومة الصينية تريد أن تعرف
which of their own agents the US government was monitoring.
أيا من وكلاتها الخاصة تتم مراقبتها من قبل الحكومة الأمريكية .
By the same token,
وعلى نفس المنوال،
in 2004, the surveillance system built into the network
في عام 2004 ،بني نظام المراقبة على الشبكات
of Vodafone Greece -- Greece's largest telephone company --
فودافون اليونان - أكبر شركات الهواتف في اليونان -
was compromised by an unknown entity,
تمت مراقبتها من كيان غير معروف ،
and that feature, the surveillance feature,
وهذه الميزة،ميزةالمراقبة،
was used to wiretap the Greek Prime Minister
استخدمت للتنصت على رئيس الوزراء اليوناني
and members of the Greek cabinet.
وأعضاء من مجلس الوزراء اليوناني .
The foreign government or hackers who did that were never caught.
لم يتم العثورأبدا على الحكومة الأجنبية أو المتسللين الذين قاموا بذلك
And really, this gets to the very problem with these surveillance features,
خلقت بالفعل مشكلة كبيرة مع ميزات المراقبة هذه ،
or backdoors.
أو الأبواب الخلفية لها
When you build a backdoor into a communications network
فعندما تقوم ببناء باب خلفي لشبكة اتصالات
or piece of technology,
أو لقطعة من التكنولوجيا،
you have no way of controlling who's going to go through it.
فليس لديك أي طريقة للتحكم فيما يحدث أو فيمن يدخل من خلالها .
You have no way of controlling
ليس لديك أي طريقة للتحكم
whether it'll be used by your side or the other side,
سواءاً كانت تستخدم من طرفك أو من طرف آخر ،
by good guys, or by bad guys.
من أشخاص سيئين أو من أشخاص طيبين .
And so for that reason, I think that it's better
لهذا أعتقد أنه من الأفضل
to build networks to be as secure as possible.
لبناء شبكات تكون آمنة قدر الإمكان.
Yes, this means that in the future,
نعم ،وهذا يعني أنه في المستقبل ،
encryption is going to make wiretapping more difficult.
سيجعل التشفيرالتنصت أكثر صعوية ،
It means that the police are going to have a tougher time
وهو ما يعني أن الشرطة ستمر بمراحل عصيبة
catching bad guys.
للقبض على الأشخاص السيئين .
But the alternative would mean to live in a world
ولكن البديل قد يعني أن تعيش في عالم
where anyone's calls or anyone's text messages could be surveilled
قد تراقب فيه أي رسالة أو اتصال لأي شخص
by criminals, by stalkers and by foreign intelligence agencies.
من خلال المجرمين ،او المطاردين ومن خلال وكالات الاستخبارات الأجنبية .
And I don't want to live in that kind of world.
وأنا لا أريد أن أعيش في مكان كهذا
And so right now, you probably have the tools
والآن ،ربما لديك الأدوات
to thwart many kinds of government surveillance
لإحباط العديد من أنواع الرقابة الحكومية
already on your phones and already in your pockets,
المتواجدة أصلا على هواتفكم المتواجدة أصلا داخل جيوبكم،
you just might not realize how strong and how secure those tools are,
وربما لا تدرك كم هي آمنة وقوية هذه الأدوات،
or how weak the other ways you've used to communicate really are.
وكم كانت الطرق القديمة التي كنت تستخدمها ضعيفة .
And so, my message to you is this:
ولذلك فإن رسالتي لكم هي :
We need to use these tools.
نحن بحاجة لاستخدام هذه الأدوات ،
We need to secure our telephone calls.
ونحن بحاجة لأن نؤمن اتصالاتنا ،
We need to secure our text messages.
ولأن نؤمن رسائلنا النصية .
I want you to use these tools.
أود منكم ان تستخدموا هذه الوسائل ،
I want you to tell your loved ones, I want you to tell your colleagues:
وأود منكم ان تخبروا أحباءكم وزملاءكم ،
Use these encrypted communications tools.
بأن يستخدموا أدوات الاتصالات المشفرة .
Don't just use them because they're cheap and easy,
لا تستخدموها لأنها سهلة ورخيصة فقط ،
but use them because they're secure.
بل لأنها آمنة أيضاً .
Thank you.
شكراً .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )